<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James R. A. Davenport</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jradavenport.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 18:32:53 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 18:32:53 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New UW Grad Foosball Table</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;petition-for-support&quot;&gt;Petition for Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;current-total-raised-span-stylecolorred1020span&quot;&gt;Current Total Raised: &lt;span style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;$1020&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-header.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cornerstone of the graduate education and experience offered by the Astronomy Department is the grad foosball table. Generations of grad students have gathered around for countless games, and in doing so forming bonds of friendship and rivalry that will last the ages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After nearly 15 years of glorious play, our beloved table has started to show it’s age. Therefore we are reaching out to you for financial support. Help us replace the foosball table with one that will last another 15 years! Do it for the Qual studying stress relief, the w(h)ine time fueled match-ups, the afternoon frivolity… and most of all, do it for the next generation of grad students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We have already received $700 of support from GPSS towards our new table!&lt;/strong&gt; Our goal is to purchase a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Tornado-Tournament-3000-Foosball-Table/dp/B001FTH4OA&quot;&gt;Tornado Tournament 3000&lt;/a&gt; (approx. $2069 + tax). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions of any amount will be graciously accepted, and your name added to a Donor Support page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added incentive to support this grad student past time, we are offering exclusive naming rights to figures for any donors of $100 or more. You may pick any player, first come first served. Only 26 available! We will write names on the figures with permanent marker. Figures that are crossed out have already been reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to support the grads and this cherished pasttime, please contact James Davenport (jrad -at- uw.edu)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Quality Animations in IDL</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-good-looking-animations-using-idl&quot;&gt;How to make good looking animations using IDL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Most of these steps work for Python or any other data visualization language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently you see animations that are generated using IDL where each frame is essentially a screen shot. This is characterized by white-on-black drawing from the default (outdated) Xwindows styling, the low image resolution/clarity, and hard to read fonts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written a step-by-step guide to rendering animation frames using IDL that get around these problems. The task is relatively simple: generate .eps file outputs, convert them to something like .jpeg using an external program, and then finally combine the frames in to a movie (or animated gif).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the full run-down, check out this post on my blog:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2015/01/making-quality-animations-in-idl.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If We Assume: Making Quality Animations in IDL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research Visualizations (Jan 2015)</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;here-are-some-visualizations-from-my-research-use-them-as-you-please-but-give-attribution&quot;&gt;Here are some visualizations from my research. Use them as you please, but give attribution.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of starspot on rotating star (left) and resulting lightcurve (right)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/HiqMF5W.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of rotating star with stylized transiting planet (used as logo in talk)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; alt=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/116912802?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Study: Gender in Conference Talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/talks.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, with help from friends and volunteers, I undertook a unique study of the gender ratios present in conference talks. We gathered data on the gender of both speakers and questioners from over 270 talks at the 223rd AAS meeting in Washington DC. Our goal is to better understand how and when people ask questions at scientific conferences, and to help define best-practices for conferences to ensure everyone can participate equally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in extending this project to future AAS meetings, as well as other scientific conferences. If you are attending/organizing an upcoming conference and wish to collect data to assist with this project, please email me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-preliminary-report-from-aas-223-is-availablehttparxivorgabs14033091&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1403.3091&quot;&gt;Our preliminary report from AAS 223 is available!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was reproduced at NAM 2014, and their excellent report is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://astrogeo.oxfordjournals.org/content/55/6/6.8&quot;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New:&lt;/strong&gt; We are working on the analysis of data from AAS 225 currently. A paper will be posted to the arXiv and the AAS.org website this semester with our new results. One interesting preliminary result appears to be: if women ask the first question of a talk, women are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more likely to ask additional questions! &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project: Elevate-ApJ</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taken from the README file of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/elevate-apj&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. Ping me if you’re interested in helping!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-to-elevate-the-readability-and-design-of-astronomy-journal-articles&quot;&gt;Working to elevate the readability and design of astronomy journal articles.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/old.png&quot; /&gt;
The design for most journal articles in astronomy is a two-column, highly condensed layout. This format makes efficient use of paper, which in turn reduces printing costs. The narrow columns are also easy to read/parse, like that of a newspaper. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all journals are changing to an online-only form of publication. This raises two important issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The web versions of these articles are difficult to read, and so most people avoid them and use the PDF versions instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The PDF versions of the articles look great on paper, but are difficult to read on a computer screen due to their layout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect journal articles are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; becoming online-only, they’re just outsourcing the printing job to their readers. &lt;strong&gt;Paper is still the best medium to read astronomy journal articles today due to the article layout.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-can-improve-this&quot;&gt;We can improve this!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By updating the layout of journal articles we hope to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase use of web/PDF article versions on computers and tablet devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve comprehension and scientific usefulness of articles themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce use of paper, trees, ink, printer/photocopier maintenance…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this we must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider the screen size and shape of the devices people use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider the human exerience with the article, top-to-bottom flow, avoiding unnecessary scrolling, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn from the single-column layout/design of sites like medium.com, and just about every news website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the PDF and web versions of articles as similar as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make figures/images, as well as tables, seamlessly integrated within the article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;astronomy6-goalsneeds&quot;&gt;.astronomy6 Goals/Needs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;discuss and create a new design for journal articles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hack together a really sloppy implementation of this design in LaTeX&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take the sources files for an article formatted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://hea-www.harvard.edu/~alexey/emulateapj/&quot;&gt;emulateapj&lt;/a&gt; (probably from the arXiv) and apply this new design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(time/skill permitting) format the article for the web as well. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can sketch the design, but would love more people to discuss them with. Perhaps each person took a screenshot of an article or website they thought was a format inspiration? Design on a white board if possible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can do some hacking in LaTeX, but other expertise/thoughts would be incredibly valuable. Should we start from the article class, or emulateapj package? This LaTeX design doesn’t have to be robust, but the primary goal is to create a demo PDF that is more pleasing to read on a computer/tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do the web version I need people who have skills. Should we try to use Markdown and MathJax? Generate a Jekyll/CSS/somethingelse template? Brute force?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resourceslinks&quot;&gt;Resources/Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.paulolyslager.com/optimal-text-layout-line-length/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.dyslexiefont.com&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.authorea.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/07/elevate-apj.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/07/elevate-apj.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research/Data Products</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-products&quot;&gt;Research Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2014ApJ...797..122D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;: the analytic M-dwarf flare model for Kepler data is coded up in IDL &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/FBeye/blob/master/aflare.pro&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2014MNRAS.440.3430D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;: The 10-dimensional stellar color locus, using &lt;em&gt;ugrizJHK&lt;/em&gt; and WISE bands 1-3. Full machine readable tables are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/wise_locus&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012ApJ...748...58D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2012&lt;/a&gt;: Predicted flare colors in SDSS and 2MASS filters for M0-M6 stars. Inlcudes IDL code, and save file, and NUV to IR spectral templates are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/flare-grid&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-products&quot;&gt;Code Products&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the full-featured Python implementation of &lt;code&gt;cubehelix&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/cubehelix&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the latest verison of my useful IDL routines, including &lt;code&gt;contour_plus&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cubehelix&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For my IDL-based flare finding suite &lt;code&gt;FBEYE&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/FBeye&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/10/30/data-products.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/10/30/data-products.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post: How to Publish in Astronomy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A younger student recently asked me what we meant by having a paper “reviewed by a referee”. This caused me to realize that “refereeing” is a term of art, and is not completely obvious to new students or laypeople. I had similar discussions with CS colleagues when I interned at MSR; we were each surprised at the differences in publication procedures between our fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So because it may someday help someone (or the process will improve and we can look back on this as an historical curiosity) here is my brief email review of how papers get published in astronomy (in the US):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;begin-email&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Begin Email:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ah, “referee”! Let me explain with a quick intro to the paper-publishing procedure used in Astronomy (note: this is NOT the same between all academic fields)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;work super hard on a paper for a long time, make it as absolutely good as possible, typo free, i’s dotted, p’s and q’s minded&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;submit online to the journal of choice (how to choose a journal is a subtle thing, no universal agreement). you send them the latex file and all figures, they compile it in to a PDF. At this stage, your paper is “submitted” (you might see that written places)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the journal assigns it an “editor” who makes sure the whole procedure from here on out works smooth. this is the person you go to w/ Q’s or problems along the way&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the editor looks over your paper and finds a “referee” (assuming your paper isn’t obviously nonsense). The referee is a colleague with some experience related to your paper, and may likely be one of the people you cite in the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;if the astronomer agrees to be the referee, they have a window of time (roughly a month) to read your paper and judge it. they will decide if it is quality science, done rigorously, explain well, appears honest, etc. If you’re just making shit up, they should be able to sniff this out.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;the referee will write her “report”, which usually will highlight what they like about the paper, and what Q’s they have. Standard practice seems to be to try and give you about 10-20 things they didn’t like, or wanted more clarification on. This report can be very harsh sometimes, and you must always remind yourself that we WANT strict referees (even when you’re cursing them about their comments on your brilliant work).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;you receive the report, and then address all the referee’s points (or don’t, but explain in detail why). When you think the paper is tuned up and better than ever, you send it BACK in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The referee has the option to either then recommend your paper for publication or send you another report…. I’ve had this process repeat 4 times once, and it was brutal. But the paper was better for it in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;once your paper is recommended for publication, the editor will probably (99.999% chance) accept it and begin the slow process of “publishing it”. This can take a few months, as the journal tunes up the language a bit in places, fixes commas, makes the paper fit the the standard rules of english for the journal (we get lots of non-native english speaking authors). In this processes your paper is “in press”, or sometimes just written as “accepted”.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;at this step you can send the paper to the arXiv. Some people do this after step (2), and I have at times, but usually you should wait until it is accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;you will then pay for the paper in most astro journals. “Page Charges” come from the author(s), and run something like $125/page (they have varying ways of calculating cost now). Thus a big paper can easily run you $2k… but this cost nominally goes towards making the articles available for everyone for free (after a year or something). this part of the system sucks, but no viable solution has been presented for astro yet.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;finally your groundbreaking work of earth-shattering brilliance is published, between 2 and 10 months usually from when you submitted, and you have a full proper reference for your CV&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most papers submitted in astronomy are eventually accepted. This is very different from other fields. Humanities can have a hard time getting articles published. In Comp Sci they use conferences like we use journals, and the acceptance rate is close to 20% for most, but no pages charges. There are many other fascinating differences, like average numbers of authors per paper, etc. CS conferences (and many other fields) usually have multiple referees per paper also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… and that is where baby papers come from&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/05/01/babypapers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/05/01/babypapers.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My Miscellaneous Papers/Talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are some miscellaneous papers and talks that I have written. I’m not sure if this is at all useful to anyone, but if you find this via websearch (or sent here by someone) and make use of it, I’d sure appreciate you letting me know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talks&quot;&gt;Talks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Slides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/nLUiT&quot;&gt;Evidence for Multiple Populations in Globular Clusters (2012)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Video: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vINb5GCtDR8&quot;&gt;The United States of Starbucks&lt;/a&gt; (2013 - Based on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2012/10/the-united-states-of-starbucks.html&quot;&gt;project from my blog&lt;/a&gt;)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;More talks related to my blog are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/p/presentations.html&quot;&gt;listed here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;miscellaneous-papers&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous Papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1303.7433&quot;&gt;Unidentified Moving Objects in Next Generation Time Domain Surveys (April 1, 2013)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/XadH0&quot;&gt;Understanding Fowler Sampling with NIC-FPS (updated 2011)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;grad-school-term-papers&quot;&gt;Grad School Term Papers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/gQJhO&quot;&gt;Multiple Populations in Globular Clusters (SDSU, 2008)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/nmH0q&quot;&gt;Herbig Haro Jets: Tracers of Accretion (SDSU 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/IGwPS&quot;&gt;Globular Clusters in Hierarchical Cosmology (SDSU 2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goo.gl/PSwVU&quot;&gt;Habitability of Planets around M Dwarfs (UW, 2010)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/02/01/misc-papers.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/02/01/misc-papers.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Post: Random Color X11 terminal for Mac</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted to make my xterm a different color, to add spice to my life. After some quick searching, I started working from the directions &lt;a href=&quot;http://entropicprincipal.blogspot.com/2006/03/picking-random-color-for-xterms.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there needed to be some modifications. I created a &lt;a href=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/randomxterm.pl&quot;&gt;perl script&lt;/a&gt; and put it at this path: &lt;code&gt;~/.randomxterm.pl&lt;/code&gt; Not all the colors look good with white text, so I needed to constrain the choices. Also I had to &lt;code&gt;chmod 755&lt;/code&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perl script needs to know the location of the X11 colors. For OSX Yosemite this file appears to be at &lt;code&gt;/opt/X11/share/X11/rgb.txt&lt;/code&gt;, and the file looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;255 250 250             snow
248 248 255             ghost white
248 248 255             GhostWhite
245 245 245             white smoke
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In X11, I then created a new terminal profile, called Color xterm, shown below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/xtermcolors.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get light/pink colored windows, so I should constrain the choices more… but it works well otherwise! Pointless and fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/xterm-random.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/01/01/randomcolors.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/01/01/randomcolors.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My IDL Routines</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Previously I had listed all my publicly available IDL routines. For the latest verison of my IDL routines, see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl&quot;&gt;GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/cubehelix_clr_sm.png&quot; onmouseover=&quot;this.src=&#39;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/cubehelix_bw_sm.png&#39;&quot; onmouseout=&quot;this.src=&#39;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/cubehelix_clr_sm.png&#39;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my flare finding suite (FBEYE), click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/FBeye&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2013/01/01/idl.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2013/01/01/idl.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
