<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James R. A. Davenport</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jradavenport.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 12:02:11 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2018 12:02:11 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Flares on Proxima Cen</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/proxima_header.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today a majorly exciting astronomical discovery was announced: a planet has been found around our &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proxima_Centauri&quot;&gt;nearest neighbor&lt;/a&gt;, and it’s named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v536/n7617/full/nature19106.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proxima b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The planet is near Earth-mass, and orbiting right in the habitable zone for Proxima Cen – It’s a huge deal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I wasn’t involved with the discovery of Proxima b, I have been working with a team of other astronomers (led primarily by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidkipping.co.uk/&quot;&gt;David Kipping&lt;/a&gt;) to study Proxima Cen. One byproduct of this work, which we are announcing today in conjunction with the Proxima b excitement, is a study of the flares from Proxima Cen. After coordinating with Guillem Anglada Escudé and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pale_red_dot&quot;&gt;Pale Red Dot&lt;/a&gt; team, we’re releasing this work today because it provides an important look at the stellar environment that Proxima b orbits in. This is naturally a critical piece of the habitability question!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##Our Work&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many pundits and armchair astronomers will tell you, Proxima Cen is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flare_star&quot;&gt;flare star&lt;/a&gt;, meaning it produces many high energy flares on its surface. These events are driven by the star’s magnetic field, and occur on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Solar_flare&quot;&gt;Sun too&lt;/a&gt;. Proxima Cen is a low mass star, called an M dwarf, which are known for sometimes exhibiting very high levels of flare activity.  M dwarf flares can produce much more X-ray and UV radiation than Solar flares. This radiation might be harmful for life, and a constant bombardment from it could even destroy a planet’s atmosphere. Ouch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our data come from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MOST_(satellite)&quot;&gt;MOST&lt;/a&gt;, a nifty &lt;em&gt;suitcase sized&lt;/em&gt; space telescope, which also happens to be Canada’s first space telescope! While the Hubble this ain’t, MOST is designed for pointing at bright stars and staring at them for long periods of time – perfect if you’re in the business of finding these randomly occurring flare events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, Proxima flares a lot (not as much as some other flare stars, mind you). In 37 days of monitoring data on Proxima we found more than 60 flares. These events have energies comparable to the larger end of Solar flares… but keep in mind Proxima is only 12% the size of the Sun! &lt;strong&gt;These flares can be so bright they can raise the total brightness of Proxima (in the visible light) by 20-50%!&lt;/strong&gt; Here’s a couple as examples from our data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/bigflares.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Sun got 50% brighter for 5 or 10 minutes… that would be a very uncomfortable day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the characteristic shape of the flares? Very rapid rise, exponential decay. I found in a previous paper using Kepler that M dwarf flares typically have two phases of decay that are general among most all flare events. What’s interesting, though I don’t fully have my head around it yet: The example at Left of Proxima follows this 2-decay law, the example on the Right does not. Huh…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##The rate of flares on Proxima Cen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stellar (and Solar) flares occur with a range of energies and durations. Typically we describe the “flare rate” as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_law&quot;&gt;power law&lt;/a&gt; distribution, with infrequent large energy events, and tons of small ones. We see this on the Sun, and for basically every other star we’ve &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.03494&quot;&gt;studied for flares&lt;/a&gt;. Proxima is no different, and shows a clear power law shape in the flare energy versus rate. Here is that result from our paper, with a few relevant energies highlighted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/rate_fig.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red line is the “power law” model. The key takeaways are both the high and low energy ends: small flares happen a lot on Proxima. While they don’t appear to produce a worrisome amount of constant UV or X-ray radiation, these small flares will (and have!) definitely made searches for any transiting Earth-mass exoplanets difficult. &lt;strong&gt;Proxima produces on average about 66 flares per day with similar amplitudes in visible light as an Earth-mass planet would block.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s frustrating!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the large-energy flare end, we still don’t understand the full impact a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superflare&quot;&gt;“superflare”&lt;/a&gt; would have on an Earth-like atmosphere, though there has been some great work on the subject (and much more is being done!) What is important for this star is that the newly discovered Proxima b is being subjected to a lot of these big flares. &lt;strong&gt;We estimate Proxima produces roughly 8 of these superflares per year.&lt;/strong&gt; If even only a few of these were to impact Proxima b, this might be very bad news for the atmosphere and anyone vacationing there… So more detailed models of how the atmosphere would truly respond (or even if it would survive) are needed, and thankfully smarter folks than me are working on it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##The Future&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, in the near future everybody and their uncle will be studying Proxima, trying to learn more about the planet (e.g. it’s size, radius, maybe even the composition).  I believe this will soon produce a “paper flare”, with a huge rise and then exponential decay in the number of papers on the Proxima Cen system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A less talked about aspect of this important low mass star is it’s rotation. Proxima rotates quite slowly,  83 days compared to ~25 days on the Sun. &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1607.03494&quot;&gt;Typically&lt;/a&gt; we see an &lt;em&gt;inverse&lt;/em&gt; connection between rotation and flare rates, with short rotation period (fast spinning) stars showing higher flare rates. Since rotation probably helps drive the star’s magnetic field, this is thought to be an age effect: stars spin slower as they age (just like a child’s top spinning on a table), which also leads to lower flare rates as they get older. Proxima flies in the face of this assumption, and flares A LOT compared to its rotation period. Interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we only have 37 days of data for Proxima, we couldn’t track the full rotation. But here’s what we caught:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/rotation.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matches nicely with the less dense tracking (but over a longer time period) shown &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1608.06291&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. With the flurry of activity I expect to follow the announcement of Proxima b, we’ll hopefully get a TON of monitoring for Proxima. With this we could track the detailed spot sizes and positions over many rotation periods, and try to determine how long the spots &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2014/04/starspots-on-kepler186.html&quot;&gt;live&lt;/a&gt;, and maybe something about their properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our part, we’re still processing the MOST data, looking for any &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z5LVcfzRDI8&quot;&gt;sign of a transit&lt;/a&gt;. Results soon on that front!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our paper is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1608.06672&quot;&gt;on the arXiv&lt;/a&gt;, and is submitted for review to the Astrophysical Journal Letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://westerntoday.wwu.edu/features/western-researcher-on-team-examining-the-impact-of-parent-star-on-newly-discovered-planet&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checkout the Press Release on this work!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This work is supported by an NSF Astronomy and Astrophysics Postdoctoral Fellowship under award AST-1501418&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2016/08/24/proxima.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2016/08/24/proxima.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>WWU Data Science Seminar</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;spring-2016&quot;&gt;Spring 2016&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Most) Tuesdays at 4pm in the Astro Lab&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am running a seminar this quarter on computational techniques for physics &amp;amp; astronomy undergraduates. This will be a series of short lectures and labs that demonstrate techniques, with optional homework “assignments”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this course is not to make you data scientists. Nor is it to make you highly skilled astronomers. Instead I hope to give you a broad overview of the content that exists, so that you are empowered to learn more! Each lesson will use actual modern astronomical data for teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;planned-lessons&quot;&gt;Planned Lessons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each lesson will point to a GitHub repository with notes, code, example data, etc. Students should submit their “homework” as Pull Requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab1&quot;&gt;Tools of the trade&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab2&quot;&gt;Algorithm 1: Do something!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab3&quot;&gt;Algorithm 2: Try to break your code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab4&quot;&gt;Data wrangling, file Input/Output&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab5&quot;&gt;Data visualization, what makes a “good” plot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab6&quot;&gt;Fitting a model to data, making measurements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/WWU-seminar-2016/tree/master/lab7&quot;&gt;Intro to machine learning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;links-for-class&quot;&gt;Links for class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.continuum.io/downloads&quot;&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;, the awesome bundled Python install. &lt;strong&gt;required&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;you will need an account here&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;you can install the &lt;a href=&quot;https://desktop.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub desktop client&lt;/a&gt; if you don’t have git on your computer&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/stephtdouglas/teaching-git-and-github&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;Stephanie Douglas’ lecture on Git and GitHub&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vallandingham.me/Quick_Git.html&quot;&gt;Really Quick Git&lt;/a&gt; by Jim Vallandingham, quick tips on setting up and using Git/GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.wwu.edu/fls/&quot;&gt;WWU Computer Science &lt;em&gt;Fraser Lecture Series&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;: The Big Data Revolution in Human and Environmental Health&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The development of this seminar is supported by the National Science Foundation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2016/03/02/seminar.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2016/03/02/seminar.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organizing Your Citations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you write a paper in astronomy, you need to provide references back to the papers. Rather than manually writing out every citation and ensuring you get the reference correct in your bibliography, make use of the \cite command and point your bibliography at a master reference library! This is all driven by a wonderful piece of tex-nology called BibTex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to organize that library, and I’ve written a helpful tutorial about doing this using BibDesk on my blog. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-we-assume-how-i-citehttpwwwifweassumecom201509how-i-citehtml&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2015/09/how-i-cite.html&quot;&gt;If We Assume: How I Cite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/09/04/bibdesk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/09/04/bibdesk.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CubeHelix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/cubehelix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011 I stumbled across a paper about color schemes for use in astronomical images (&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1108.5083&quot;&gt;Dave Green 2011&lt;/a&gt;). I immediately translated the included Fortran code into IDL for use in my own research, and became a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2013/05/cubehelix-or-how-i-learned-to-love.html&quot;&gt;vocal advocate&lt;/a&gt; for the use of “CubeHelix”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CubeHelix can now be used in many visualiation languages, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl/blob/master/cubehelix.pro&quot;&gt;IDL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/cubehelix&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/11415064&quot;&gt;d3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2013/08/cubehelix-now-for-tableau.html&quot;&gt;Tableau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My CubeHelix code has been incorporated in several other packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Fanning’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.idlcoyote.com/idldoc/cg/cgloadct.html&quot;&gt;Coyote IDL library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Galloy’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.idldev.com/mglib/vis/color/mg_cubehelix.html&quot;&gt;IDL Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HEALPix &lt;a href=&quot;http://healpix.sourceforge.net/html/idlnode44.htm&quot;&gt;IDL library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://p3d.sourceforge.net/index.php?page=refs&quot;&gt;P3D&lt;/a&gt; Fiber-fed spectrograph reduction tool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Randolph Voorhies’ OpenCV &lt;a href=&quot;http://randvoorhies.github.io/rcv/classrcv_1_1cubehelix.html&quot;&gt;Python library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matt Davis’ palettable &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jiffyclub/palettable/tree/master/palettable/cubehelix&quot;&gt;Python module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/05/06/cubehelix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/05/06/cubehelix.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Step-by-Step Guide to 1D Spectroscopy in Python</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This guide is a rough draft explanation of how to reduce DIS data from start to finish with &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt;. Note, this entire process is reproduced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/pydis/wiki/function:-autoreduce&quot;&gt;autoreduce&lt;/a&gt; helper function. In this simple example we’ll assume you have all the needed calibration files in the working directory, that you are on a linux/mac for a couple shell commands, and that there is only 1 science frame to analyze. We will only do the RED chip in this case. The procedure is identical for the BLUE chip, but due to different Signal/Noise or color of the source some parameters may need tweaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the code has been evolving, this guide has been moved. In a future version of this page I will have a complete guide including sample data and images…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;look-at-the-pydis-github-wikihttpsgithubcomjradavenportpydiswikimanual-reduction-guide-for-the-latest-version-of-this-guide&quot;&gt;Look at the &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/pydis/wiki/Manual-Reduction-Guide&quot;&gt;GitHub Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for the latest version of this guide!&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/13/spectra2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/13/spectra2.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>pyDIS: a Python-based longslit reduction package</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of people talk a big game about the need for new and open software tools in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/4Y55NZH.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my shelf are at &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; 4 books that could teach you how to reduce photometric (imaging) data well. There are many tutorials for writing your own aperture photometry pipeline. I even wrote one myself with about &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl/blob/master/simplephot.pro&quot;&gt;500 lines of code&lt;/a&gt;! This data analysis problem is considered “easy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these books, and most people who write simple photo-pipelines like mine, ignore spectroscopy. By adding the wavelength dimension (and losing at least 1 spatial dimension) we make the problem exponentially harder. I don’t know of a good book that walks you through this - if you have one, please send me the title so I can buy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best manual for CCD spectroscopy &lt;a href=&quot;http://iraf.noao.edu/iraf/ftp/iraf/docs/spect.ps.Z&quot;&gt;with IRAF is from 1992&lt;/a&gt;, and is seriously helpful. A good “theory” paper on CCD spectroscopy that I’ve used is &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1992ASPC...23..160W&quot;&gt;Wagner (1992)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when a practitioner of astronomy wants to reduce spectroscopy, they first seek out another wizard who remembers the order of divine incantations to whisper to IRAF. Then they pray. Then they swear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-wrong-with-that&quot;&gt;So, what’s wrong with that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two philosophical bones to pick here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Single object, longslit spectroscopy is “simple” data. It shouldn’t be daunting to use, especially when it becomes increasing valueable as a compliment to “Big Photometry”. It’s 2015, there should be a great toolbox for this!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data from instruments should come reduced for you! We build (custom made, hugely expensive) general-use instruments so everyone can do science without having to be an optics or electrical engineer. Large surveys know this well: people need to use their data without being a computer scientist or image processing professional. When you build an instrument, build a pipeline!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brighter-future&quot;&gt;A brighter future.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/spectra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first goal with &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is to provide a turn-key solution for reducing and understanding longslit spectroscopy, which could ideally be done in real time. So far I have only used data from the low/medium resolution &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apo.nmsu.edu&quot;&gt;APO 3.5-m&lt;/a&gt; “Dual Imaging Spectrograph” (DIS). Therefore, many instrument specific assumptions are being made. &lt;strong&gt;As of now, the software works for a first-order reduction of data&lt;/strong&gt;, and may be good enough for some science purposes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; can reduce an entire night of DIS data in under 1 minute with almost no button clicking&lt;/strong&gt; (provided your data is simple, moderate S/N and you have all the right standards and calibrations…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not an expert Python programmer, nor a deep expert on spectroscopy. I am just a frustrated scientist who wants this tool to exist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second goal is to &lt;strong&gt;“put up or shut up”&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m tired of people (like me) saying “boo IRAF”, or “we need new tools”, and not building them. That’s why I applaud projects like astropy, emcee, and astroML: they aren’t just complaining, they’re doing. So this is my attempt at doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-call-to-arms&quot;&gt;A call to arms.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is not done, and not fully stable. Still, I think it’s more complete than most other packages out there for quickly analyzing longslit spectroscopy (well, if you’re using DIS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know other spectroscopy pipelines exist, even some &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/crawfordsm/pyspectrograph&quot;&gt;powerful ones&lt;/a&gt; in Python. My plea for you is: make them simple to use! Many I have looked at appear too complicated for me to use, especially without a robust worked example (not just a Hello World). Some are basically impossible to use for other instruments (and maybe &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is too…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s is a classic argument: if you write good documentation, people will use your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you hate what I’ve created: good! Make it better, or make something else! Does &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; unnecessarily reproduce or ignore functionality from your amazing codebase? Let me know how I can fix that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what I’ve created: help! Try to use it, send me feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re building a new general purpose instrument: please write a reduction pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/01/spectra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/01/spectra.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New UW Grad Foosball Table</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt; Petition for Support. &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; Update: &lt;span style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;We made it!&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-header.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cornerstone of the graduate education and experience offered by the Astronomy Department is the grad foosball table. Generations of grad students have gathered around for countless games, and in doing so forming bonds of friendship and rivalry that will last the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After nearly 15 years of glorious play, our beloved table has started to show it’s age. Therefore we are reaching out to you for financial support. Help us replace the foosball table with one that will last another 15 years! Do it for the Qual studying stress relief, the w(h)ine time fueled match-ups, the afternoon frivolity… and most of all, do it for the next generation of grad students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to purchase a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Tornado-Tournament-3000-Foosball-Table/dp/B001FTH4OA&quot;&gt;Tornado Tournament 3000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions of any amount will be graciously accepted, and your name added to a Donor Support page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added incentive to support this grad student past time, we are offering exclusive naming rights to figures for any donors of $100 or more. You may pick any player, first come first served. Only 26 available! We will write names on the figures with permanent marker. Figures that are crossed out have already been reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many thanks to the current and former grad students, and the UW GPSS, for their support!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Quality Animations in IDL</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-good-looking-animations-using-idl&quot;&gt;How to make good looking animations using IDL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Most of these steps work for Python or any other data visualization language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently you see animations that are generated using IDL where each frame is essentially a screen shot. This is characterized by white-on-black drawing from the default (outdated) Xwindows styling, the low image resolution/clarity, and hard to read fonts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written a step-by-step guide to rendering animation frames using IDL that get around these problems. The task is relatively simple: generate .eps file outputs, convert them to something like .jpeg using an external program, and then finally combine the frames in to a movie (or animated gif).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the full run-down, check out this post on my blog:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2015/01/making-quality-animations-in-idl.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If We Assume: Making Quality Animations in IDL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research Visualizations (Jan 2015)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;###Here are some visualizations from my research. Use them as you please, but give attribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of starspot on rotating star (left) and resulting lightcurve (right)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/HiqMF5W.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of rotating star with stylized transiting planet (used as logo in talk)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; alt=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/116912802?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Study: Gender in Conference Talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/talks.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, with help from friends and volunteers, I undertook a unique study of the gender ratios present in conference talks. We gathered data on the gender of both speakers and questioners from over 270 talks at the 223rd AAS meeting in Washington DC. Our goal is to better understand how and when people ask questions at scientific conferences, and to help define best-practices for conferences to ensure everyone can participate equally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-more-information-see-this-pagehttpjradavenportgithubiogenderstudy&quot;&gt;For more information, see &lt;a href=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/gender_study&quot;&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
