<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James R. A. Davenport</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://jradavenport.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2015 13:37:46 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2015 13:37:46 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Organizing Your Citations</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When you write a paper in astronomy, you need to provide references back to the papers. Rather than manually writing out every citation and ensuring you get the reference correct in your bibliography, make use of the \cite command and point your bibliography at a master reference library! This is all driven by a wonderful piece of tex-nology called BibTex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll need to organize that library, and I’ve written a helpful tutorial about doing this using BibDesk on my blog. Check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-we-assume-how-i-citehttpwwwifweassumecom201509how-i-citehtml&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2015/09/how-i-cite.html&quot;&gt;If We Assume: How I Cite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Sep 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/09/04/bibdesk.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/09/04/bibdesk.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CubeHelix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/cubehelix.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August of 2011 I stumbled across a paper about color schemes for use in astronomical images (&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1108.5083&quot;&gt;Dave Green 2011&lt;/a&gt;). I immediately translated the included Fortran code into IDL for use in my own research, and became a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2013/05/cubehelix-or-how-i-learned-to-love.html&quot;&gt;vocal advocate&lt;/a&gt; for the use of “CubeHelix”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CubeHelix can now be used in many visualiation languages, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl/blob/master/cubehelix.pro&quot;&gt;IDL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/cubehelix&quot;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bl.ocks.org/mbostock/11415064&quot;&gt;d3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2013/08/cubehelix-now-for-tableau.html&quot;&gt;Tableau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My CubeHelix code has been incorporated in several other packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Fanning’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.idlcoyote.com/idldoc/cg/cgloadct.html&quot;&gt;Coyote IDL library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Galloy’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.idldev.com/mglib/vis/color/mg_cubehelix.html&quot;&gt;IDL Library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HEALPix &lt;a href=&quot;http://healpix.sourceforge.net/html/idlnode44.htm&quot;&gt;IDL library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://p3d.sourceforge.net/index.php?page=refs&quot;&gt;P3D&lt;/a&gt; Fiber-fed spectrograph reduction tool&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Randolph Voorhies’ OpenCV &lt;a href=&quot;http://randvoorhies.github.io/rcv/classrcv_1_1cubehelix.html&quot;&gt;Python library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matt Davis’ palettable &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jiffyclub/palettable/tree/master/palettable/cubehelix&quot;&gt;Python module&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/05/06/cubehelix.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/05/06/cubehelix.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Step-by-Step Guide to 1D Spectroscopy in Python</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This guide is a rough draft explanation of how to reduce DIS data from start to finish with &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt;. Note, this entire process is reproduced in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/pydis/wiki/function:-autoreduce&quot;&gt;autoreduce&lt;/a&gt; helper function. In this simple example we’ll assume you have all the needed calibration files in the working directory, that you are on a linux/mac for a couple shell commands, and that there is only 1 science frame to analyze. We will only do the RED chip in this case. The procedure is identical for the BLUE chip, but due to different Signal/Noise or color of the source some parameters may need tweaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the code has been evolving, this guide has been moved. In a future version of this page I will have a complete guide including sample data and images…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;look-at-the-pydis-github-wikihttpsgithubcomjradavenportpydiswikimanual-reduction-guide-for-the-latest-version-of-this-guide&quot;&gt;Look at the &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/pydis/wiki/Manual-Reduction-Guide&quot;&gt;GitHub Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for the latest version of this guide!&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/13/spectra2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/13/spectra2.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>pyDIS: a Python-based longslit reduction package</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of people talk a big game about the need for new and open software tools in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/4Y55NZH.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 700px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my shelf are at &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; 4 books that could teach you how to reduce photometric (imaging) data well. There are many tutorials for writing your own aperture photometry pipeline. I even wrote one myself with about &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl/blob/master/simplephot.pro&quot;&gt;500 lines of code&lt;/a&gt;! This data analysis problem is considered “easy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these books, and most people who write simple photo-pipelines like mine, ignore spectroscopy. By adding the wavelength dimension (and losing at least 1 spatial dimension) we make the problem exponentially harder. I don’t know of a good book that walks you through this - if you have one, please send me the title so I can buy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best manual for CCD spectroscopy &lt;a href=&quot;http://iraf.noao.edu/iraf/ftp/iraf/docs/spect.ps.Z&quot;&gt;with IRAF is from 1992&lt;/a&gt;, and is seriously helpful. A good “theory” paper on CCD spectroscopy that I’ve used is &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1992ASPC...23..160W&quot;&gt;Wagner (1992)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, when a practitioner of astronomy wants to reduce spectroscopy, they first seek out another wizard who remembers the order of divine incantations to whisper to IRAF. Then they pray. Then they swear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-whats-wrong-with-that&quot;&gt;So, what’s wrong with that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have two philosophical bones to pick here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Single object, longslit spectroscopy is “simple” data. It shouldn’t be daunting to use, especially when it becomes increasing valueable as a compliment to “Big Photometry”. It’s 2015, there should be a great toolbox for this!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data from instruments should come reduced for you! We build (custom made, hugely expensive) general-use instruments so everyone can do science without having to be an optics or electrical engineer. Large surveys know this well: people need to use their data without being a computer scientist or image processing professional. When you build an instrument, build a pipeline!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-brighter-future&quot;&gt;A brighter future.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introducing: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/spectra&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first goal with &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is to provide a turn-key solution for reducing and understanding longslit spectroscopy, which could ideally be done in real time. So far I have only used data from the low/medium resolution &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apo.nmsu.edu&quot;&gt;APO 3.5-m&lt;/a&gt; “Dual Imaging Spectrograph” (DIS). Therefore, many instrument specific assumptions are being made. &lt;strong&gt;As of now, the software works for a first-order reduction of data&lt;/strong&gt;, and may be good enough for some science purposes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; can reduce an entire night of DIS data in under 1 minute with almost no button clicking&lt;/strong&gt; (provided your data is simple, moderate S/N and you have all the right standards and calibrations…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not an expert Python programmer, nor a deep expert on spectroscopy. I am just a frustrated scientist who wants this tool to exist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second goal is to &lt;strong&gt;“put up or shut up”&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m tired of people (like me) saying “boo IRAF”, or “we need new tools”, and not building them. That’s why I applaud projects like astropy, emcee, and astroML: they aren’t just complaining, they’re doing. So this is my attempt at doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-call-to-arms&quot;&gt;A call to arms.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is not done, and not fully stable. Still, I think it’s more complete than most other packages out there for quickly analyzing longslit spectroscopy (well, if you’re using DIS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know other spectroscopy pipelines exist, even some &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/crawfordsm/pyspectrograph&quot;&gt;powerful ones&lt;/a&gt; in Python. My plea for you is: make them simple to use! Many I have looked at appear too complicated for me to use, especially without a robust worked example (not just a Hello World). Some are basically impossible to use for other instruments (and maybe &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; is too…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s is a classic argument: if you write good documentation, people will use your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you hate what I’ve created: good! Make it better, or make something else! Does &lt;em&gt;pyDIS&lt;/em&gt; unnecessarily reproduce or ignore functionality from your amazing codebase? Let me know how I can fix that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like what I’ve created: help! Try to use it, send me feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re building a new general purpose instrument: please write a reduction pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/01/spectra.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/04/01/spectra.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New UW Grad Foosball Table</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;petition-for-support&quot;&gt;Petition for Support.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;update-span-stylecolorredwe-made-itspan&quot;&gt;Update: &lt;span style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;We made it!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-header.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cornerstone of the graduate education and experience offered by the Astronomy Department is the grad foosball table. Generations of grad students have gathered around for countless games, and in doing so forming bonds of friendship and rivalry that will last the ages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After nearly 15 years of glorious play, our beloved table has started to show it’s age. Therefore we are reaching out to you for financial support. Help us replace the foosball table with one that will last another 15 years! Do it for the Qual studying stress relief, the w(h)ine time fueled match-ups, the afternoon frivolity… and most of all, do it for the next generation of grad students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal is to purchase a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Tornado-Tournament-3000-Foosball-Table/dp/B001FTH4OA&quot;&gt;Tornado Tournament 3000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributions of any amount will be graciously accepted, and your name added to a Donor Support page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added incentive to support this grad student past time, we are offering exclusive naming rights to figures for any donors of $100 or more. You may pick any player, first come first served. Only 26 available! We will write names on the figures with permanent marker. Figures that are crossed out have already been reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/foos-names.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update&lt;/em&gt;: We have placed the order for our new Tornado Tournament 3000. Many thanks to the current and former grad students, and the UW GPSS, for their support!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/03/10/foosball.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Quality Animations in IDL</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-make-good-looking-animations-using-idl&quot;&gt;How to make good looking animations using IDL&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: Most of these steps work for Python or any other data visualization language&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frequently you see animations that are generated using IDL where each frame is essentially a screen shot. This is characterized by white-on-black drawing from the default (outdated) Xwindows styling, the low image resolution/clarity, and hard to read fonts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written a step-by-step guide to rendering animation frames using IDL that get around these problems. The task is relatively simple: generate .eps file outputs, convert them to something like .jpeg using an external program, and then finally combine the frames in to a movie (or animated gif).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the full run-down, check out this post on my blog:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ifweassume.com/2015/01/making-quality-animations-in-idl.html&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If We Assume: Making Quality Animations in IDL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/02/19/animations.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research Visualizations (Jan 2015)</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;here-are-some-visualizations-from-my-research-use-them-as-you-please-but-give-attribution&quot;&gt;Here are some visualizations from my research. Use them as you please, but give attribution.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of starspot on rotating star (left) and resulting lightcurve (right)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/HiqMF5W.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animated gif of rotating star with stylized transiting planet (used as logo in talk)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; alt=&quot;http://i.imgur.com/QUf4Yee.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//player.vimeo.com/video/116912802?byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2015/01/15/vis.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Study: Gender in Conference Talks</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/talks.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, with help from friends and volunteers, I undertook a unique study of the gender ratios present in conference talks. We gathered data on the gender of both speakers and questioners from over 270 talks at the 223rd AAS meeting in Washington DC. Our goal is to better understand how and when people ask questions at scientific conferences, and to help define best-practices for conferences to ensure everyone can participate equally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very interested in extending this project to future AAS meetings, as well as other scientific conferences. If you are attending/organizing an upcoming conference and wish to collect data to assist with this project, please email me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-preliminary-report-from-aas-223-is-availablehttparxivorgabs14033091&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1403.3091&quot;&gt;Our preliminary report from AAS 223 is available!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study was reproduced at NAM 2014, and their excellent report is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://astrogeo.oxfordjournals.org/content/55/6/6.8&quot;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New:&lt;/strong&gt; We are working on the analysis of data from AAS 225 currently. A paper will be posted to the arXiv and the AAS.org website this semester with our new results. One interesting preliminary result appears to be: if women ask the first question of a talk, women are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more likely to ask additional questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/08/gender.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Project: Elevate-ApJ</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Taken from the README file of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/elevate-apj&quot;&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. Ping me if you’re interested in helping!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;working-to-elevate-the-readability-and-design-of-astronomy-journal-articles&quot;&gt;Working to elevate the readability and design of astronomy journal articles.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem…&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img align=&quot;right&quot; src=&quot;http://jradavenport.github.io/assets/old.png&quot; /&gt;
The design for most journal articles in astronomy is a two-column, highly condensed layout. This format makes efficient use of paper, which in turn reduces printing costs. The narrow columns are also easy to read/parse, like that of a newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly all journals are changing to an online-only form of publication. This raises two important issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The web versions of these articles are difficult to read, and so most people avoid them and use the PDF versions instead.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The PDF versions of the articles look great on paper, but are difficult to read on a computer screen due to their layout.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In effect journal articles are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; becoming online-only, they’re just outsourcing the printing job to their readers. &lt;strong&gt;Paper is still the best medium to read astronomy journal articles today due to the article layout.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-can-improve-this&quot;&gt;We can improve this!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By updating the layout of journal articles we hope to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;increase use of web/PDF article versions on computers and tablet devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improve comprehension and scientific usefulness of articles themselves&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reduce use of paper, trees, ink, printer/photocopier maintenance…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To accomplish this we must:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider the screen size and shape of the devices people use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider the human exerience with the article, top-to-bottom flow, avoiding unnecessary scrolling, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;learn from the single-column layout/design of sites like medium.com, and just about every news website.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make the PDF and web versions of articles as similar as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;make figures/images, as well as tables, seamlessly integrated within the article.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;astronomy6-goalsneeds&quot;&gt;.astronomy6 Goals/Needs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;discuss and create a new design for journal articles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hack together a really sloppy implementation of this design in LaTeX&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take the sources files for an article formatted with &lt;a href=&quot;http://hea-www.harvard.edu/~alexey/emulateapj/&quot;&gt;emulateapj&lt;/a&gt; (probably from the arXiv) and apply this new design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(time/skill permitting) format the article for the web as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can sketch the design, but would love more people to discuss them with. Perhaps each person took a screenshot of an article or website they thought was a format inspiration? Design on a white board if possible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can do some hacking in LaTeX, but other expertise/thoughts would be incredibly valuable. Should we start from the article class, or emulateapj package? This LaTeX design doesn’t have to be robust, but the primary goal is to create a demo PDF that is more pleasing to read on a computer/tablet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do the web version I need people who have skills. Should we try to use Markdown and MathJax? Generate a Jekyll/CSS/somethingelse template? Brute force?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resourceslinks&quot;&gt;Resources/Links&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.paulolyslager.com/optimal-text-layout-line-length/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.dyslexiefont.com&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;https://www.authorea.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/07/elevate-apj.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/11/07/elevate-apj.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Research/Data Products</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-products&quot;&gt;Research Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2014ApJ...797..122D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;: the analytic M-dwarf flare model for Kepler data is coded up in IDL &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/FBeye/blob/master/aflare.pro&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2014MNRAS.440.3430D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;: The 10-dimensional stellar color locus, using &lt;em&gt;ugrizJHK&lt;/em&gt; and WISE bands 1-3. Full machine readable tables are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/wise_locus&quot;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2012ApJ...748...58D&quot;&gt;Davenport et al. 2012&lt;/a&gt;: Predicted flare colors in SDSS and 2MASS filters for M0-M6 stars. Inlcudes IDL code, and save file, and NUV to IR spectral templates are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/flare-grid&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;code-products&quot;&gt;Code Products&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the full-featured Python implementation of &lt;code&gt;cubehelix&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/cubehelix&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For the latest verison of my useful IDL routines, including &lt;code&gt;contour_plus&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;cubehelix&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/jradavenport_idl&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;For my IDL-based flare finding suite &lt;code&gt;FBEYE&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jradavenport/FBeye&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/10/30/data-products.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://jradavenport.github.io/2014/10/30/data-products.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
